<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../grimm-schema-combined.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<tales>
    <tale>
        <metadata>
            <title>Rapunzel</title>
            <year>1812</year>
            <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
            <editor>Göttingen: Verlag der Dieterichschen Buchhandlung</editor>
            <translator>D. L. Ashliman</translator>
            <language>English</language>
            <number>12</number>
        </metadata>
        <story>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="man and woman">Once upon a time there was
                    a man and a <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife"
                        reference="wife">woman</character> who had long, but to no avail, wished for
                    a child.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="wife">Finally the <character
                        reference="wife" marital-status="wife" child-status="mother"
                        >woman</character> came to believe that the good Lord would fulfill
                        <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="wife"
                        >her</character> wish.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="man and woman">Through the small rear
                    window of these people's house they could see into a splendid garden that was
                    filled with the most beautiful flowers and herbs.</act>
                <act type="being" effect="ambiguous" agent="garden">The garden was surrounded by a
                    high wall,</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="all">and no one dared enter,</act><act
                    type="being" effect="hostile" agent="sorceress"> because it belonged to a
                    sorceress who possessed great power and was feared by everyone.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">One day the woman was standing at
                    this window,</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">and she saw a bed planted with the
                    most beautiful rapunzel.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">It looked so fresh and green that
                    she longed for some.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">It was her greatest desire to eat
                    some of the rapunzel.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">This desire increased with every
                    day,</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife"/><act type="being"
                    effect="hostile" agent="wife">and not knowing how to get any, she became
                    miserably ill.</act></p>
            <p><act type="being" effect="hostile" agent="husband">Her husband was frightened, and
                    asked her</act>, <dialogue speaker="husband" stateofbeing="neutral">"What ails
                    you, dear wife?"</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="wife" stateofbeing="negative">"Oh,"</dialogue><act type="doing"
                    effect="hostile" agent="wife">she answered,</act><dialogue speaker="wife"
                    stateofbeing="negative">"if I do not get some rapunzel from the garden behind
                    our house, I shall die."</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="husband">The man, who loved her dearly,
                    thought,</act>
                <dialogue speaker="husband" stateofbeing="negative">"Before you let your <character
                        child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="wife"
                        >wife</character> die, you must get her some of the rapunzel, whatever the
                    cost."</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="husband">So just as it was getting dark he
                    climbed over the high wall into the <character child-status="childless"
                        reference="evil woman" marital-status="unmarried">sorceress's</character>
                    garden, hastily dug up a handful of rapunzel, and took it to his <character
                        marital-status="wife" reference="wife" child-status="mother"
                        >wife.</character></act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">She immediately made a salad from
                    it, which she devoured eagerly.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">It tasted so very good to her that
                    by the next day her desire for more had grown threefold.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="wife">If she were to have any peace, the
                    man would have to climb into the garden once again.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="husband">Thus he set forth once again
                    just as it was getting dark. But no sooner than he had climbed over the wall
                    than, to his horror, he saw the sorceress standing there before him.</act></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="negative">"How can you dare," <character
                        child-status="childless" reference="evil woman" marital-status="unmarried"
                        >she</character> asked with an angry look, "to climb into my garden and like
                    a thief to steal my rapunzel? You will pay for this."</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="husband" stateofbeing="positive">"Oh," he answered, "Let mercy
                    overrule justice. I came to do this out of necessity. My <character
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="wife" child-status="mother"
                        >wife</character> saw your rapunzel from our window, and such a longing came
                    over her, that she would die, if she did not get some to eat."</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="being" effect="ambiguous" agent="evil woman">The sorceress's anger abated
                    somewhat, and she said,</act>
                <dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="negative">If things are as you say, I
                    will allow you to take as much rapunzel as you want. But under one condition:
                    You must give me the <character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="Rapunzel">child</character> that your
                    wife will bring to the world. It will do well, and I will take care of it like a
                    mother."</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="husband">In his fear the man agreed to
                    everything.</act>
            </p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="wife" receiver="evil woman" io="Rapunzel"
                    >When the woman gave birth, the sorceress appeared, named the little girl
                    Rapunzel, and took her away. Rapunzel became the most beautiful child under the
                    sun.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="evil woman" receiver="Rapunzel">When she
                    was twelve years old, the sorceress locked her in a tower that stood in a forest
                    and that had neither a door nor a stairway, but only a tiny little window at the
                    very top.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="evil woman" io="Rapunzel">When the
                    sorceress wanted to enter, she stood below and called out:</act></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="neutral">Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down
                    your hair to me.</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="being" effect="benevolent" agent="Rapunzel">Rapunzel had splendid long
                    hair, as fine as spun gold.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="Rapunzel" receiver="evil woman">When she
                    heard the sorceress's voice, she untied her braids, wound them around a window
                    hook, let her hair fall twenty yards to the ground, and the sorceress climbed up
                    it.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">A few years later it happened
                    that a king's son was riding through the forest.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">As he approached the tower he
                    heard a song so beautiful that he stopped to listen. It was Rapunzel, who was
                    passing the time by singing with her sweet voice.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">The prince wanted to climb up to
                    her, and looked for a door in the tower, but none was to be found.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">He rode home, but the song had so
                    touched his heart that he returned to the forest every day and listened to
                    it.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">One time, as he was thus
                    standing behind a tree, he saw the sorceress approach, and heard her say:</act>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="neutral">Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down
                    your hair.</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="Rapunzel" receiver="evil woman">Then
                    Rapunzel let down her strands of hair, and the sorceress climbed up them to
                    her.</act></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="prince" stateofbeing="positive">"If that is the ladder into the
                    tower, then sometime I will try my luck."</dialogue></p>
            <p>And the next day, just as it was beginning to get dark, he went to the tower and
                called out:</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="prince" stateofbeing="positive">Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your
                    hair.</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="prince" io="Rapunzel">The hair fell
                    down, and the prince climbed up.</act></p>
            <p><act type="being" effect="hostile" agent="Rapunzel">At first Rapunzel was terribly
                    frightened when a man such as she had never seen before came in to her.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="prince" receiver="Rapunzel">However,
                    the prince began talking to her in a very friendly manner, telling her that his
                    heart had been so touched by her singing that he could have no peace until he
                    had seen her in person. Then Rapunzel lost her fear, and when he asked her if
                    she would take him as her husband,</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="Rapunzel"><character
                        child-status="childless" reference="Rapunzel" marital-status="unmarried"
                        >she</character> thought,</act>
                <dialogue speaker="Rapunzel" stateofbeing="neutral">He would rather have me than
                    would old Frau Gothel."</dialogue>
                <act type="doing" receiver="prince" agent="Rapunzel" effect="benevolent">She said
                    yes and placed her hand into his.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" agent="Rapunzel" effect="ambiguous">She said,</act>
                <dialogue speaker="Rapunzel" stateofbeing="positive">I would go with you gladly, but
                    I do not know how to get down. Every time that you come, bring a strand of silk,
                    from which I will weave a ladder. When it is finished I will climb down, and you
                    can take me away on your horse."</dialogue>
                <act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="prince and Rapunzel">They arranged that
                    he would come to her every evening, for the old woman came by day.</act></p>
            <p><act type="being" effect="ambiguous" agent="evil woman">The sorceress did not notice
                    what was happening</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="Rapunzel" receiver="evil woman">until
                    one day Rapunzel said to her,</act>
                <dialogue speaker="Rapunzel" stateofbeing="neutral">Frau Gothel, tell me why it is
                    that you are more difficult to pull up than is the young prince, who will be
                    arriving any moment now?"</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="negative">"You godless child," cried the
                    sorceress. "What am I hearing from you? I thought I had removed you from the
                    whole world, but you have deceived me nonetheless."</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="evil woman" receiver="Rapunzel">In her
                    anger she grabbed Rapunzel's beautiful hair, wrapped it a few times around her
                    left hand, grasped a pair of scissors with her right hand, and snip snap, cut it
                    off. And she was so unmerciful that she took Rapunzel into a wilderness where
                    she suffered greatly.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="evil woman" receiver="Rapunzel">On the
                    evening of the same day that she sent Rapunzel away, the sorceress tied the
                    cut-off hair to the hook at the top of the tower,</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">and when the prince called
                    out:</act></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="prince" stateofbeing="positive">Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your
                    hair.</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="evil woman">she let down the
                hair.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="prince" io="evil woman">The prince climbed
                    up, but above, instead of his beloved Rapunzel, he found the sorceress, who
                    peered at him with poisonous and evil looks.</act></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="evil woman" stateofbeing="negative">"Aha!" she cried scornfully.
                    "You have come for your Mistress Darling, but that beautiful bird is no longer
                    sitting in her nest, nor is she singing any more. The cat got her, and will
                    scratch your eyes out as well. You have lost Rapunzel. You will never see her
                    again."</dialogue></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="prince">The prince was overcome with grief,
                    and in his despair he threw himself from the tower. He escaped with his life,
                    but the thorns into which he fell poked out his eyes. Blind, he wandered about
                    in the forest, eating nothing but grass and roots, and doing nothing but weeping
                    and wailing over the loss of his beloved wife.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="prince">Thus he wandered about miserably
                    for some years, finally happening into the wilderness where Rapunzel lived
                    miserably with the twins that she had given birth to.</act></p>
            <p><act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">He heard a voice and thought it
                    was familiar.</act>
                <act type="doing" effect="benevolent" agent="prince and Rapunzel">He advanced toward
                    it, and as he approached, Rapunzel recognized him, and crying, threw her arms
                    around his neck. Two of her tears fell into his eyes, and they became clear once
                    again, and he could see as well as before. He led her into his kingdom, where he
                    was received with joy, and for a long time they lived happily and
                    satisfied.</act></p>
        </story>
    </tale>
    <tale>
        <metadata>
            <title>Rapunzel</title>
            <year>1812</year>
            <author>Jacob Grimm</author>
            <author>Wilhelm Grimm</author>
            <language>German</language>
            <number>12</number>
        </metadata>
        <story>
            <p>Es war einmal ein Mann und eine <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="wife" reference="wife">Frau</character>, die hatten sich schon
                lange ein Kind gewünscht und nie eins bekommen, endlich aber ward die <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="wife" reference="wife">Frau</character>
                guter Hoffnung. Diese Leute hatten in ihrem Hinterhaus ein kleines Fenster, daraus
                konnten sie in den Garten einer Fee sehen, der voll von Blumen und Kräutern stand,
                allerlei Art, keiner aber durfte es wagen, in den Gar- ten hineinzugehen. Eines
                Tages stand die <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife"
                    reference="wife">Frau</character> an diesem Fenster und sah hinab, da erblickte
                    <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife" reference="wife"
                    >sie</character> wunderschöne Rapunzeln auf einem Beet und wurde so lüstern
                darnach, und wußte doch, daß <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="wife" reference="wife">sie</character> keine davon bekommen
                konnte, daß <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife"
                    reference="wife">sie</character> ganz abfiel und elend wurde. Ihr Mann erschrack
                endlich und fragte nach der Ursache; <dialogue speaker="wife"
                    stateofbeing="negative">„ach wenn ich keine von den Rapunzeln aus dem Garten
                    hinter unserm Haus zu essen kriege, so muß ich sterben.“</dialogue> Der Mann,
                welcher sie gar lieb hatte, dachte, es mag kosten was es will, so willst du ihr doch
                welche schaffen, stieg eines Abends über die hohe Mauer und <act type="being"
                    effect="ambiguous" agent="husband">stach in aller Eile eine Hand voll Rapunzeln
                    aus</act>, die er seiner <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="wife" reference="wife">Frau</character> brachte. Die <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="wife" reference="wife">Frau</character>
                machte sich sogleich Salat daraus, und aß <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="wife" reference="wife">sie</character> in vollem Heißhunger auf.
                    <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife" reference="wife"
                    >Sie</character> hat- ten ihr aber so gut, so gut geschmeckt, daß <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="wife" reference="wife">sie</character>
                den andern Tag noch dreimal soviel Lust bekam. Der Mann sah wohl, daß keine Ruh
                wäre, also stieg er noch einmal in den Garten, allein er erschrack gewaltig, als die
                Fee darin stand und ihn heftig schalt, daß er es wage in ihren Gar- ten zu kommen
                und daraus zu stehlen. Er ent- schuldigte sich, so gut er konnte, mit der Schwan-
                gerschaft seiner <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife"
                    reference="wife">Frau</character>, und wie gefährlich es sey, ihr dann etwas
                abzuschlagen, endlich sprach die Fee: <dialogue speaker="fairy"
                    stateofbeing="neutral">„ich will mich zufrieden geben und dir selbst gestatten
                    Rapunzeln mitzunehmen, so viel du willst, wofern du mir das Kind geben wirst,
                    womit deine <character child-status="childless" marital-status="wife"
                        reference="wife">Frau</character> jetzo geht.“</dialogue> In der Angst sagte
                der Mann alles zu, und als die <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="wife" reference="wife">Frau</character> in Wochen kam, erschien
                die Fee sogleich, nannte das kleine <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Mädchen Rapunzel</character> und
                nahm <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">es</character> mit sich fort. </p>

            <p>Dieses <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character> wurde das schönste Kind unter der
                Sonne, wie es aber zwölf Jahr alt war, so schloß <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">es</character> die Fee in einen
                hohen hohen Thurm, der hatte weder Thür noch Treppe, nur bloß ganz oben war ein
                kleines Fensterchen. Wenn nun die Fee hinein wollte, so stand sie unten und rief: </p>

            <p><dialogue speaker="fairy" stateofbeing="neutral">„<character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>,
                        <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                        reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>! laß mir dein Haar
                    herunter.“</dialogue></p>

            <p><character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >Rapunzel</character> hatte aber prächtige Haare, fein wie gesponnen Gold, und
                wenn die Fee so rief, so <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel">band
                        <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                        reference="rapunzel">sie</character> sie los</act>, <act type="doing"
                    effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel">wickelte <character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">sie</character> oben um
                    einen Fen- sterhaken</act> und dann <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous"
                    agent="rapunzel">fielen die Haare zwanzig Ellen tief hinunter</act> und die Fee
                    <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="fairy" io="rapunzel">stieg daran
                    hinauf.</act></p>

            <p>Eines Tages kam nun ein junger Königs- sohn durch den Wald, wo der Thurm stand, sah
                das schöne <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character> oben am Fenster ste- hen und hörte
                    <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">sie</character> mit so süßer Stimme singen, daß er sich
                ganz in <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">sie</character> verliebte. Da aber keine Thüre im Thurm war
                und keine Leiter so hoch reichen konnte, so gerieth er in Verzweiflung, doch ging er
                alle Tage in den Wald hin, bis er einstmals die Fee kommen sah, die sprach: </p>

            <p><dialogue speaker="fairy" stateofbeing="neutral">„<character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>,
                        <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                        reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>! laß dein Haar
                    herunter.“</dialogue></p>

            <p>Darauf sah er wohl, auf welcher Leiter man in den Thurm kommen konnte. Er hatte sich
                aber die Worte wohl gemerkt, die man sprechen muß- te, und des andern Tages, als es
                dunkel war, ging er an den Thurm und sprach hinauf: </p>

            <p><dialogue speaker="prince" stateofbeing="neutral">„<character
                        child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                        >Rapunzel</character>, <character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>, laß
                    dein Haar herunter!“</dialogue></p>

            <p>da <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel">ließ <character
                        child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                        >sie</character> die Haare los</act>, und wie sie unten waren, <act
                    type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="prince">machte er sich daran fest</act>
                und <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel" io="prince">wurde hin-
                    aufgezogen</act>. </p>

            <p><character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >Rapunzel</character> erschrack nun anfangs, bald aber gefiel <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >ihr</character> der junge König so gut, daß <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">sie</character> mit ihm
                verabredete, er solle alle Tage kommen und hinaufgezogen werden. So lebten
                    <character child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">sie</character> lustig und in Freuden eine geraume Zeit,
                und die Fee kam nicht dahinter, bis eines Tages das <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >Rapunzel</character> anfing und zu <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">ihr</character> sagte: <dialogue
                    speaker="rapunzel" stateofbeing="neutral">„sag' sie mir doch <character
                        child-status="adopted" marital-status="unmarried" reference="fairy">Frau
                        Gothel</character>, meine Kleiderchen werden mir so eng und wollen nicht
                    mehr passen.“</dialogue> Ach du gottlo- ses <character child-status="childless"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Kind</character>, sprach die
                Fee, was muß ich von dir hören, und sie merkte gleich, wie sie betrogen wäre, und
                war ganz aufgebracht. Da <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="fairy"
                    io="rapunzel">nahm sie die schönen Haare <character child-status="childless"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzels</character></act>,
                    <act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="fairy" receiver="rapunzel">schlug sie
                    ein paar Mal um ihre linke Hand</act>, griff eine Scheere mit der rechten und
                    <act type="doing" effect="hostile" agent="fairy" receiver="rapunzel">ritsch,
                    ritsch, waren sie abge- schnitten</act>. Darauf verwieß sie <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >Rapunzel</character> in eine Wüstenei, wo es <character
                    child-status="childless" marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel"
                    >ihr</character> sehr kümmerlich erging und <character child-status="mother"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">sie</character> nach Verlauf
                einiger Zeit Zwillinge, <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel">einen
                    Knaben und ein Mädchen gebar.</act></p>

            <p>Denselben Tag aber, wo sie <character child-status="mother"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character> ver- stoßen
                hatte, machte die Fee Abends die abge- schnittenen Haare oben am Haken fest, und als
                der Königssohn kam; </p>

            <p><dialogue speaker="prince" stateofbeing="neutral">„<character child-status="mother"
                        marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>,
                        <character child-status="mother" marital-status="unmarried"
                        reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character>, laß dein Haar
                    herunter!“</dialogue></p>

            <p>so ließ sie zwar die Haare nieder, allein wie erstaunte der Prinz, als er statt
                seines gelieb- ten <character child-status="mother" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">Rapunzels</character> die Fee oben fand. <dialogue
                    speaker="fairy" stateofbeing="negative">„Weißt du was, sprach die erzürnte Fee,
                        <character child-status="mother" marital-status="unmarried"
                        reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character> ist für dich Bösewicht auf immer
                    verloren!“</dialogue></p>

            <p>Da wurde der Königssohn ganz verzwei- felnd, und stürzte sich gleich den Thurm hinab,
                das Leben brachte er davon, aber die beiden Augen hatte er sich ausgefallen, traurig
                irrte er im Wald herum, aß nichts als Gras und Wurzeln, und that nichts als weinen.
                Einige Jahre nachher geräth er in jene Wüstenei, wo <character child-status="mother"
                    marital-status="unmarried" reference="rapunzel">Rapunzel</character> kümmerlich
                mit ihren Kindern lebte, ihre Stimme däuchte ihm so bekannt, in dem- selben
                Augenblick erkannte <character child-status="mother" marital-status="unmarried"
                    reference="rapunzel">sie</character> ihn auch und <act type="doing"
                    effect="ambiguous" agent="rapunzel" receiver="prince">fällt ihm um den
                    Hals</act>. Zwei von ihren Thrä- nen fallen in seine Augen, da werden sie wie-
                der klar, und er kann damit sehen, wie sonst. </p>
        </story>
    </tale>
</tales>
