<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../grimm-schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<tale>
<metadata>
    <title>The Twelve Brothers</title>
    <year>1812</year>
    <author>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm</author>
    <language>English</language>
    <number>9</number>
</metadata>
<story>
    <p>Once upon a time there were a king and a <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="queen">queen</character>. They <act type="being" effect="benevolent" agent="queen">lived happily together</act> and <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="queen">had twelve children</act>, all boys. One day the king said to his <character marital-status="wife" child-status="mother" reference="queen">wife</character>, <dialogue>"If our thirteenth child, which you are soon going to bring into the world, is a girl, then the twelve others shall die, so that her wealth may be great, and so that she alone may inherit the kingdom."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Indeed, he had twelve coffins made. They were filled with wood shavings and each was fitted with a coffin pillow. He had them put in a locked room, and <act type="doing" agent="king" effect="ambiguous" receiver="queen">gave the key to the queen</act>, <act effect="hostile" agent="king" type="doing" receiver="queen">ordering her to tell no one about them</act>.</p>

    <p><act agent="queen" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">The <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="queen">mother</character> sat and mourned</act> the entire day, until the youngest son -- who was always with her, and who was named Benjamin after the Bible -- said to her, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="negative">"Dear <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="queen">mother</character>, why are you so sad?"</dialogue></p>

    <p><dialogue stateofbeing="negative" speaker="queen">"Dearest child,"</dialogue> she answered, <dialogue speaker="queen" stateofbeing="negative">"I cannot tell you."</dialogue></p>

    <p>However, <act effect="ambiguous" receiver="queen" type="doing" agent="benjamin">he would not leave her in peace</act>, until <act agent="queen" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she unlocked the room</act> and <act agent="queen" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">showed him the coffins</act>, already filled with wood shavings.</p>

    <p>Then she said, <dialogue stateofbeing="negative" speaker="queen">"My dearest Benjamin, your father had these coffins made for you and your eleven brothers. If I bring a girl into the world, you are all to be killed and buried in them."</dialogue></p>

    <p>As <act effect="ambiguous" type="doing" agent="queen">she spoke and cried</act>, <act agent="benjamin" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="queen">her son comforted her</act>, saying, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="negative">"Don't cry, dear mother. We will take care of ourselves and run away."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Then she said, <dialogue stateofbeing="negative" speaker="queen">Go out into the woods with your eleven brothers. One of you should climb the highest tree that you can find. Keep watch there and look toward the castle tower. If I give birth to a little son, I will raise a white flag. If I give birth to a little daughter, I will raise a red flag, and then you should escape as fast as you can, and may God protect you. I will get up every night and pray for you, in the winter that you may warm yourselves near a fire, and in the summer that you may not suffer from the heat."</dialogue></p>

    <p>After <act effect="benevolent" receiver="twelvebrothers" type="doing" agent="queen">she had blessed her children</act>, they went out into the woods. One after the other of them kept watch, sitting atop the highest oak tree and looking toward the tower. After eleven days had passed, and it was Benjamin's turn, he saw that a flag had been raised. It was not the white one, but instead the red blood-flag, decreeing that they all were to die.</p>

    <p>When the boys heard this they became angry and cried out, <dialogue speaker="twelvebrothers">"Are we to suffer death for the sake of a girl! We swear that we will take revenge. Wherever we find a girl, her red blood shall flow."</dialogue></p>

<p>Then they went deeper into the woods, and in its middle, where it was darkest, they found a little bewitched house that was empty.</p>

<p>They said, <dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"We will live here. You, Benjamin, you are the youngest and weakest. You shall stay at home and keep house. We others will go and get things to eat."</dialogue></p>

<p>Thus they went into the woods and shot rabbits, wild deer, birds, and doves, and whatever they could eat. These they brought to Benjamin, and he had to prepare them to satisfy their hunger. They lived together in this little house for ten years, but the time passed quickly for them.</p>

    <p><character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">The little daughter</character> that <character marital-status="wife" reference="queen" child-status="mother">their mother, the queen</character>, had given birth to was now grown up. <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">She had a good heart, a beautiful face, and a golden star on her forehead</character>.</p>

    <p>Once on a large washday <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she saw twelve men's shirts in the laundry</act> and asked her <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="queen">mother</character>, <dialogue speaker="daughter" stateofbeing="neutral">"Whose are these twelve shirts? They are much too small for father."</dialogue></p>

    <p><character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="queen">The queen</character> answered with a heavy heart, <dialogue stateofbeing="negative" speaker="queen">"Dear child, they belong to your twelve brothers."</dialogue></p>

    <p><character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">The girl</character> said, <dialogue speaker="daughter" stateofbeing="neutral">"Where are my twelve brothers? I have never even heard of them."</dialogue></p>

<p>She answered, <dialogue speaker="queen" stateofbeing="negative">"Only God knows where they are. They are wandering about in the world."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Then <act effect="ambiguous" type="doing" agent="queen" receiver="daughter">she took the girl</act>, <act effect="ambiguous" type="doing" agent="queen" receiver="daughter">unlocked the room for her</act>, and <act effect="ambiguous" type="doing" agent="queen" receiver="daughter">showed her the twelve coffins</act> with the wood shavings and the coffin pillows.</p>

    <p><dialogue stateofbeing="negative" speaker="mother">"These coffins,"</dialogue> she said, <dialogue speaker="mother" stateofbeing="negative">"were intended for your brothers, but they secretly ran away before you were born,"</dialogue> and <act effect="ambiguous" type="doing" agent="queen" receiver="daughter">she told her how everything had happened</act>.</p>

    <p>Then <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">the girl</character> said, <dialogue stateofbeing="positive" speaker="daughter">"Dear <character marital-status="wife" reference="queen" child-status="mother">mother</character>, don't cry. I will go and look for my brothers."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Then <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she took the twelve shirts</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">went forth into the great woods</act>. <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">She walked the entire day</act>, in the evening <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">coming to the bewitched little house</act>.</p>

    <p><act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">She went inside</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">found a young lad</act>, who asked, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"Where do you come from, and where are you going?"</dialogue></p>

    <p><act agent="benjamin" effect="benevolent" type="being" receiver="daughter">He was astounded that she was so beautiful</act>, that <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she was wearing royal clothing</act>, and that <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she had a star on her forehead</act>.</p>

    <p><dialogue speaker="daughter" stateofbeing="positive">"I am <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">a princess</character> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">am looking for my twelve brothers</act>. I will walk on as long as the sky is blue, until I find them."</dialogue> <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous" receiver="benjamin">She also showed him the twelve shirts that belonged to them</act>.</p>

    <p><act agent="benjamin" effect="benevolent" type="being" receiver="daughter">Benjamin saw that it was his sister</act>, and said, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="positive">"I am Benjamin, your youngest brother."</dialogue></p>

    <p><act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="benevolent">She  began to cry for joy</act>, and Benjamin did so as well. <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="benjamin">They kissed and embraced one another with great love</act>.</p>

    <p>Then he said, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="negative">"Dear <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">sister</character>, I must warn you that we have agreed that every girl whom we meet must die."</dialogue></p>

<p>She said, <dialogue stateofbeing="positive" speaker="daughter"> "I will gladly die, if I can thus redeem my twelve brothers."</dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"No,"</dialogue> he answered, <dialogue stateofbeing="positive" speaker="benjamin">"you shall not die. Sit under this tub until our eleven brothers come, and I will make it right with them."</dialogue></p>

<p>She did this, and when night fell they came home from the hunt. As they sat at the table eating, they asked, <dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin">"What is new?"</dialogue></p>

<p>Benjamin said, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"Don't you know anything?"</dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin">"No,"</dialogue> they answered.</p>

<p>He continued speaking, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"You have been in the woods while I stayed at home, but I know more than you do."</dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"Then tell us,"</dialogue> they shouted.</p>

<p>He answered, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"If you will promise me that the next girl we meet shall not be killed."</dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"Yes,"</dialogue> they all shouted. <dialogue speaker="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"We will show her mercy. Just tell us."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Then he said, <dialogue speaker="benjamin" stateofbeing="neutral">"Our sister is here,"</dialogue> and lifted up the tub. <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">The princess came forth</act> in her royal clothing and with the golden star on her forehead, so beautiful, delicate, and fine.</p>

    <p><act agent="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" effect="benevolent" receiver="daughter" type="doing">They all rejoiced, falling around her neck and kissing her</act>, and <act agent="twelvebrothersnotbenjamin" type="being" effect="benevolent" receiver="daughter">they loved her with all their hearts</act>.</p>

    <p><act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">Now she stayed at home with Benjamin</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous" receiver="benjamin">helped him with the work</act>. The eleven went into the woods and captured wild game, deer, birds, and doves, so they would have something to eat. Their <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing" io="wildgame"><character marital-status="unmarried" reference="daughter" child-status="childless">sister</character> and Benjamin prepared it all</act>. <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">They gathered wood</act> for cooking, herbs for the stew, and <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">put the pot onto the fire</act> so a meal was always ready when the eleven came home. <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">She also kept the house in order</act>, and <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">made up the beds white and clean</act>. The brothers were always satisfied, and they lived happily with her.</p>

    <p>One time the two of them <act type="doing" effect="ambiguous" agent="daughter">had prepared a good meal at home</act>, and so <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">they sat together</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">ate and drank</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="being" effect="ambiguous">were ever so happy</act>. Now there was a little garden next to the bewitched house, and in it there were twelve lilies, the kind that are called "students." Wanting to bring some pleasure to her brothers, <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">she picked the twelve flowers</act>, intending to give one to each of them when they were eating. But in the same instant that she picked the flowers, the twelve brothers were transformed into twelve ravens, and they flew away above the woods. The house and the garden disappeared as well.</p>

    <p>Now the <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">poor girl</character> was alone in the wild woods. Looking around, <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing" receiver="old_woman">she saw an <character marital-status="unmarried" reference="old_woman" child-status="childless">old women</character> standing next to her</act>.</p>

    <p>The <character marital-status="unmarried" reference="old_woman" child-status="childless">old woman</character> said, <dialogue speaker="old_woman" stateofbeing="negative">"<character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">My child</character>, what have you done?" Why did you not leave the twelve white flowers standing? Those were your brothers, and now they have been transformed into ravens forever."</dialogue></p>

    <p><character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">The girl</character> said, <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">crying</act>, <dialogue speaker="daughter" stateofbeing="negative">"Is there no way to redeem them?"</dialogue></p>

    <p><dialogue speaker="old_woman" stateofbeing="neutral">"No,"</dialogue> said the <character marital-status="unmarried" reference="old_woman" child-status="childless">old woman</character>, <dialogue speaker="old_woman" stateofbeing="negative">"There is only one way in the world, and it is so difficult that you will never redeem them. You must remain silent for seven whole years, neither speaking nor laughing. If you speak a single word, even if all but one hour of the seven years has passed, then it will all be for nothing, and your brothers will be killed by that one word."</dialogue></p>

    <p>Then <character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">the girl</character> said in her heart, <dialogue speaker="daughter" stateofbeing="positive">"I know for sure that I will redeem my brothers."</dialogue></p>

    <p><act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">She went and found a tall tree</act> and <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous" io="tall_tree">climbed to its top</act>, where <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she sat and span</act>, without speaking and without laughing.</p>

    <p>Now it came to pass that a king was hunting in these woods. He had a large greyhound that ran to the tree where <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous"><character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">the girl</character> was sitting</act>. It jumped about, yelping and barking up the tree. The king came, <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">saw the beautiful princess</act> with the golden star on her forehead, and <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">was so enchanted by her beauty</act> that <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">he shouted up to her, asking her to become his wife</act>. <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">She gave him no answer</act>, but <act agent="daughter" effect="ambiguous" type="doing">nodded with her head</act>. Then he himself climbed the tree, <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">carried her down</act>, <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">set her on his horse</act>, and <act agent="other_king" effect="benevolent" type="doing" receiver="daughter">took her home with him</act>.</p>

    <p>Their wedding was celebrated with great pomp and joy, but <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="ambiguous"><character marital-status="unmarried" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">the bride</character> neither spoke nor laughed</act>.</p>

    <p>After they had lived a few years happily together, <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="other_kings_mother">the king's mother</character>, who <act agent="other_kings_mother" type="being" effect="hostile">was a wicked woman</act>, <act agent="other_kings_mother" type="being" effect="hostile" receiver="daughter">began to slander <character marital-status="wife" child-status="childless" reference="daughter">the young queen</character></act>, saying to the king, <dialogue speaker="other_kings_mother" stateofbeing="negative">"You have brought home a common beggar woman for yourself. Who knows what kind of godless things she is secretly doing. Even if she is a mute and cannot speak, she could at least laugh. Anyone who does not laugh has an evil conscience."</dialogue></p>

    <p>At first the king did not want to believe this, but the <character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="other_kings_mother">old woman</character> kept it up so long, <act agent="other_kings_mother" type="doing" effect="hostile" receiver="daughter">accusing her of so many wicked things</act>, that the king finally let himself be convinced, and <act agent="other_king" type="doing" effect="hostile" receiver="daughter">he sentenced her to death</act>.</p>

    <p>A great fire was lit in the courtyard, where she was to be burned to death. The king stood upstairs at his window, looking on with crying eyes, for <act agent="other_king" type="being" effect="ambiguous" receiver="daughter">he still loved her dearly</act>. She had already been bound to the stake, and the fire was licking at her clothing with its red tongues, when the last moment of the seven years passed.</p>

    <p>A whirring sound was heard in the air, and twelve ravens approached, landing together. As they touched the earth, <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="twelvebrothers">it was her twelve brothers, whom she had redeemed</act>. They ripped the fire apart, put out the flames, and <act agent="twelvebrothers" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="daughter">freed their sister</act>, <act agent="twelvebrothers" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="daughter">kissing and embracing her</act>.</p>

    <p>Now that she could open her mouth and speak, <act agent="daughter" type="doing" effect="benevolent" receiver="other_king">she told the king why she had remained silent and had never laughed</act>.</p>
 
    <p>The king rejoiced to hear that she was innocent, and they all lived happily together until they died. The <act agent="other_kings_mother" type="doing" effect="ambiguous"><character child-status="mother" marital-status="wife" reference="other_kings_mother">wicked stepmother</character> was brought before the court and placed in a barrel filled with boiling oil and poisonous snakes</act>, and <act agent="other_kings_mother" type="doing" effect="ambiguous">she died an evil death</act>.</p>
</story>
</tale>


